[Music]
say I give you the deep learning book
along with the question how is
convolution equivalent with respect to
translation what would you do to answer
this question
well one way you can do this is to read
the entire book and assuming you
remember everything you've read try to
answer the question but there's a better
way since it's a question on convolution
I flip to the chapter on convolution
neural networks then I find equivalence
as one of the properties and read out
that page or at least that part of the
page which do you think is a faster
method if we read the entire text like
in the first method answering the
question may take us a few weeks but in
the second method the same can be done
within a few minutes that's a very big
difference furthermore our answer while
reading the entire book may be more
vague as it's based on too much
information what did we do differently
here in the former case we didn't focus
on any part of the book specifically
whereas in the latter case we focused
our attention to the chapter on
convolution neural networks and then
further focused our attention to the
part where the concept of equal variance
is explained this second approach would
be the exact thought process many of us
humans would take it's quite intuitive
given this example scenario we can now
better define atencion atencion
mechanisms found in neural networks is
somewhat similar to that found in humans
they focus in high resolution on certain
parts of the input while the rest of the
input is in low resolution or blurred in
this video I'm going to talk about the
attention mechanism applied on image
inputs
let's take a look at visual attention at
a higher level consider the problem of
determining appropriate captions for an
input image based on the papers show
tell and attend this normally consists
of two steps first is to encode the
image in an internal vector
representation H using a convolution
neural network and then we decode H into
word vectors signifying the captions
using a recurrent neural network the
problem with this method is when
generating a single word of the caption
the LST M looks at the entire image
representation H every time this is not
very efficient as usually we generate
different words of a caption looking at
different and specific parts of an image
to solve this problem we create n
different non-overlapping sub regions
hence H I would be the internal feature
representation used to generate the
eighth word it is not necessarily the
representation of the I 3 gene of the
original image I'll explain this in a
bit for now the figure on screen is a
high-level diagram of attention when the
decoder decides on a caption for every
word it only looks at specific regions
of the image leading to a more accurate
description now that's good but how does
it exactly decide the region or regions
to consider this is the crux of the
attention mechanism an attention unit
considers all sub regions and contexts
as its input and it outputs the weighted
arithmetic mean of these regions
arithmetic mean is the inner product of
actual values and their probabilities
how are these probabilities and weights
determined they are determined using the
context C context represents everything
that recurrent neural network has output
until now
let's take a closer look at what happens
we have input regions Y from the
convolution neural net and the context
see from the RN these inputs are applied
to weights which constitute the learn
about parameters of the attention unit
this means the weight vectors update as
we get more training data we apply a
tange
activation so that of very high values
tend to have very small differences and
be close to one and very low values also
a very small difference is closer to
minus one this leads to a much smoother
choice of regions of interest within
each sub region it is more fine-grained
so to speak
note we don't necessarily have to apply
a tange function we only need to ensure
the regions that we output are relevant
to the context in the simplest form this
similarity can be determined with a
simple dot product between the regions Y
and the context C the more similar they
are the higher is the product hence the
output is guaranteed to weight the more
relevant region why I hire the
difference of using the simple inner
product and tange function would be grin
you ality of the output regions of
interest
tange is more fine-grained with less
choppy and smoother parts of sub regions
chosen regardless of how they are
calculated these M's are then passed
through a softmax function which outputs
them as probabilities s finally we take
the inner product of this probability
vector s and the sub regions Y to get
the final output Z of relevant regions
of the entire image understand the
probabilities as correspond to the
relevance of the sub regions Y given the
context C now there are two types of
attention mechanisms the first is soft
attention and then we have hard
attention the main difference here is
that in soft attention the main relevant
region C consists of different parts of
different sub regions wide
in heart attention the main relevant
region Z consists of only one of the
regions why I'll explain them both in
detail the entire mechanism of attention
that I described until now is all soft
attention Z has relevant parts of
different regions soft attention is
deterministic
so deterministic what's that a system is
said to be deterministic if the
application of an action a on a state s
always leads to the same state s prime a
dumb example would be you're at a corner
of your room at coordinates 0 0 and
you're facing forward consider an action
a which is moving 5 feet forward the
system is now at a new state with the
coordinates 5 0 and still facing forward
no matter how many times you stand at
the corner of your room forward facing
and walk five feet forward you will
always end up 5 feet from the door and
facing forward try it trust me it works
hence the system is deterministic let us
apply the same concept to soft attention
initially we have an image just split
into a number of regions why with an
input context see this is our initial
state on the application of soft
attention we end up with a localized
image representing the new state s Prime
these regions of interest are determined
from Z the RO eyes will always be the
same regardless of how many times we
execute soft attention with these same
inputs this is because we consider all
the regions Y anyways to determine Z now
consider heart attention looking at the
architecture heart attention is very
similar to soft attention however
instead of taking the weighted
arithmetic mean of all regions heart
attention only considers one region
randomly so heart attention is a
stochastic process now stochastic when
you hear the word stochastic think about
randomness in such a stochastic process
performing an action a on a state s may
lead to different states every time
typical example is like in a board game
with the dice like snakes and ladders
the initial state is the position of the
players the action is rolling a dice and
depending on the roll there are multiple
possibilities for the next board state
what makes hard attention stochastic is
that a region Y I is chosen randomly
with the probability si this means that
the more relevant a region Y I as a
whole is relevant to the context then
greater the chance it is chosen for
determining the next word of the caption
using the word captions output until now
by the RNN that is H along the current
regions of interest in an image
determined by the attention mechanism
the RNN now tries to predict the next
word in the caption as far as
performance is concerned in the papers
show attend Intel released by the
University of Toronto and University of
Montreal in 2016
results vary with the data set soft and
heart attention both perform decently
well with heart attention performing it
slightly better this is pretty cool
right so where else can we use attention
attention is not only used for image
inputs for example neural machine
translation nmt systems they are used to
translate one language to another words
are fed in a sequence to an encoder one
after another and the sentence is
terminated by a specific input word or
symbol once complete the special signal
initiates the decoder phase where the
translated words are generated another
cool application would be Microsoft's
attention generative adversarial
networks or Microsoft's attention gann
that can create images from text through
natural language processing it can
perform fine-grained tasks like
generating parts of an image from a
single word in the description
another application would be in the
paper of teaching machines to read and
comprehend the altars do the same thing
I talked about in the beginning of the
video a recurrent neural network takes
some text and a question as input and it
is made to output an answer here are
some things to remember
attention involves focus in high
resolution on certain parts of an input
while the rest of the input is in low
resolution or is blurred two types of
attention are soft attention and hard
attention soft attention is
deterministic
while hard attention is stochastic
attention can be used for non image
inputs like neural machine translation
attention Gantz and answering questions
from text and that's all I have for you
now hope you guys got some newfound
understanding of attention and its
applications in this video I have left a
link to the main paper show attend intel
with other papers and blog posts in the
description down below don't forget to
give the video a thumbs up and subscribe
for more awesome content please
subscribe please you did it right
guys